overruled
a couple of small little mistakes
in there has been corrected as well
and that's at this location on the web
I also have this URL at the end of my talk
I'm going to start with a brief history
of the MIPS platform
I go into this in a lot of detail
in my paper
so I'm going to just hit
some of the highlights here.
interesting parts here are that there are
two implementations of MIPS
one's a thirty-two bit implementation
one's a sixty-four bit implementation
that evolved over time
initially each of the implementations
was cumulative
with a prior implementation
so a MIPS VI or MIPS V processor
will implement anything MIPS IV implemented
and
over time this was decided
that not to be such a good idea
so the way this MIPS
ISA's that are available
are MIPS 32 and MIPS 64
and those define
a base set in the number of options
that can be added
options for DSD processing, options for multiple instruction
execution at the same time, SIMV sorts of things
and so that's kind of the history on MIPS in a nutshell
the other interesting piece was that happened with MIPS
is the original
MIPS ISA didn't define the TLBs
and all that and how that was interacting
with the CPUs
there were a number of variations
over time and when the never embedded MIPS
ISA's were created
that information was specified as well
so that it's easier to write one kernel
that will run on each of the processors
after they got some experience with
the different processors
they updated the spec to come up with
MIPS32r2 and MIPS64r2
these are enhancements for viewing with
primarily with multiple issue
highly parallel processors
one the things you would have to do
prior to that changing
the CLB you would execute
a number of no ops so that
the processor pipeline would flush
and on MIPS R4000 you need there was six
and on MIPS R10000 you need there was twelve
some of the newer processors you are going to know
how many you had
to execute because so many things were executing in parallel
so they created some new instructions to
help you out with that
plus a couple of other things
for making embedding easier
and those are the two
core ISA's that FreeBSD
primarily targets
are the embedded
MIPS ABIs
the ABIs sorry the ISAs
for prior MIPS chips
probably would work with FreeBSD MIPS
nobody has taken the time to make them work
the other interesting thing
back in MIPS history is
there are a number of different
ABIs
the original 32 bit ABI
which was later remained to o32
which was
for the R2000 and 3000
specified 32 bit registers
and a MIPS 2
ISA those replaced when SGI introduced 4000 based
machines with n32 and n64
n64 is
a fairly straight forward
64 bit ABI there's
nothing really all that weird about it
except the one weird thing for all MIPS ABIs is that
it's specified all the library code
has to be picked code even for static linking
n32 is a weird hybrid
and I'll get into that a little bit later
but it's
an ABI that's designed
to allow transition from old code to new code
here in this context old code to new code
was code written before 1995 or so
to new code which was being written since then
with 64 bit
it has a number of interesting
idiosyncrasies
that happened when you tried to squeeze
when you tried to
fit 32 bit ABI to 64 bit registers
and now
come later for some of the work that
has done
So FreeBSD MIPS is been
around for a very long time
it's not just been around in the FreeBSD tree
for along time initial ports
for FreeBSD MIPS
was in the 3.x time frame
due to persistence
did a FreeBSD port to a
custom piece of
silicon that they had which had a MIPS core
embedded in it and
and excuse me
and at the time they were looking for people in the FreeBSD
community to commit this port back to the FreeBSD tree
there were a number of problems though
you couldn't just run this port
on a
particular on any given MIPS platform
you couldn't run it on a SGI MIPS
you couldn't run it on an old deck station
it had a
high number of
tweaks in it for the custom silicon that they ran it
so interested the developer community was
ya we like a MIPS port but
we don't have any hardware to run it against
and it would be a big effort to take the code that
you have done and do it to
the platforms that we have access to
so
there were a lot of talks back and forth
in this time frame
between members of the
FreeBSD community
and Juniper networks
and
they basically went nowhere
the fist internet bubble crashed
so it languished
everywhere except
inside of juniper
where they kept developing it
and improving it over the years
so
about the same time
I became interested in getting
FreeBSD up and running on the MIPS
so I got
the basic LibC support
going and the basic tool chains
going in the tree
with some help from David O'Brien
and
kept trying to talk up different
people to try their for people who had more time than I had
to get interested in it
to pick up the banner
and this was
right after the internet
bubble burst
people didn't have a lot of spare time
they were too busy
just surviving to do a MIPS port
so consequently the initial
work that I had done in 1999
was removed
three years later in 2002
when no progress had been made
a few years later
Julie Mallett started putting FreeBSD
to the SGI platform and he
got his SGI box booting into single user mode
but his situation
changed he didn't have
the time to
take it from single use mode to
multi user mode to make it stable
he did this work in the Perforce repository
with one of the early examples of a
large body of work that was done
outside
FreeBSD
CVS tree
but inside of Perforce so that interested parties
can look at it and work on it
since it was
SGI boxes and at the time
people call it the SGI boxes
it was targeting
more obsolete
part of the developers in the community
really supported this also as
Julie would admit
she took a lot of shortcuts
to get the pot up and running
that were the basis of
a lot of the stability problems that
she found out wound out having when she
tried to go from single user to multi user
so the important thing here though
is that all of this code existed
Perforce repository
and just kept existing out in the Perforce repository
Julie took a lot of that code from that BSD and
in an effort to make it simpler
I think wrote portions of it
but it also was simpler
so there was
carefully selected pieces of code wound up in
later projects
and that was one of the value of this effort
once Julie lost interest in this she announced it
publicly: I don't have time to do this
this is going nowhere
BSDcan
three years ago now
myself and
Peter Wemm
John Baldwin and
a few other people
Sat down and realized hey
there's a lot of people
who want FreeBSD
and FreeBSD's features to run
in embedded platform to run on
very cheap MIPS routers that
were becoming available at the time
and we decided hey
let's see if we can get
a jump start on this MIPS project
if the going generates
some excitement
may be we'll hit critical mass
and we did
a number of things
well we got the tool chain
up and running
we got the kernel building
the MI portions
not the MD portions
unfortunately
we made a mistake on how we
were doing this
we included a secret part of the Perforce repository
so there was no commit mails
nobody saw what was going on
nobody knew what was happening
and the thinking at the time was
well we'll
get it to a certain point and then announce it
we don't want to have a public failure on our hands
so instead we had a private failure on our hands
because
nobody knew it was there
nobody was excited about it
we could access the code
so that was
not a good idea
you're an
open source project
you should learn from this mistake
to make sure you do things in an open manner
so about six months after
we started this project
it was clear that it was going nowhere
about this time there were two individuals
Wojciech Koszek and
Oleksandr Tymoshenko
approached different members of the
had approached Julie and said hey I want to take your
old port and make it better
and they talked to Julie about
our new port and
she says well
there's this new port
so these two took
the best pieces of
both of these efforts
and got FreeBSD MIPS
booting on
emulated hardware
at the end of 2006
and then on real hardware in 2007
on a couple of different MIPS processors
and then
things started to
languish a little bit
except for one piece
Cavium Networks
saw this work and took one of the
MIPS 2 snapshots
and ported it to their
Octeon series of processors
The Octeon is a multicore MIPS processor
that has a
the number of additional units in it
for dealing with networking efficiently
dealing with moving packets
scheduling work
among the multiple CPUs
it's a fairly interesting platform
also
Bruce Sampson
got it running on the
the Sentry-5
series Broadcom
parts
the Sentry-5 series
which I'll get to in a little bit
is different than
the Linksys WRTs
It's a higher quality implementation of MIPS
so he was able to do that
so
we were seeing some small incremental steps
this little thing is added
that little thing is added
but it was still moving very slowly
it took a year and a half to get to this point
Juniper work up again
or at least decided
we need to upgrade from
our FreeBSD 4.x
to FreeBSD 6.1
to remain competitive
there's a number of features
in FreeBSD as it happens
we need to have those in our product
so they upgraded
their version of FreeBSD
called JunOS
to 6.1
as part
of this effort they upgraded all of
their MIPS ports they had several different ones
unfortunately
they weren't able just to release these ports
because they had been written with
material that came under NDA
they weren't allowed to disclose some of the
intellectual property for the specific MIPS chips
but they recognized the value of having
a good FreeBSD MIPS support
so they
approached me with a
sanitized port that they had done
they ported their code to an idealized MIPS machine
one of the ones that conformed with the
MIPS 64 MIPS 32 ISA
they gave this code to me in
September of 2007
and I started reviewing it
but the review was very slow
it was a busy time for me
I was in the process
of changing jobs
so in
November of 2007
I started working for CISCO systems
CISCO systems had spearheaded an effort
to put FreeBSD as a part of the next
generation of routers they were producing
or at least for a couple of business units
and ultimately that project was abandoned
but before it was abandoned
we got FreeBSD MIPS up and going
we merged
MIPS 2 code with the Juniper code
the Juniper code was very good
for things like PMAP and VM system
the basic nuts and bolts of the system
from a memory process point of view
very stable
it had one driver in it SIO
one driver
wasn't really enough to produce a viable system
so we took
all the drivers and startup code
from the MIPS 2 effort
that had been going on
so drivers for particular SOC
mix drivers for
switches that were in these devices and so forth
we ported those over and
got everything booting
and just before
BSDcan 2008
we committed all this to the
tree except
for the Cavium port
it had similar
IP issues that we needed to resolve
before we committed it
so today we target MIPS 32 MIPS 64
we run
only o32 binaries we've not added the
n32 and n64 support
it runs on
about six different
SOCs different cores
I'll get into those in a few minutes
there are some SMP support
for the different multicore chips
but its not
well tested we did not enable it
because we could not test it to
see if it works
beyond one early experiment we did
we've fixed a lot of stability
bugs since then we don't know if you turn
it back on whether it'll work or not
so here's the different
SOCs that FreeBSD MIPS
runs on today
it runs on the
ADM5120 in
united states anyway there are number of
small routers or
tunnel servers
wireless devices as well
that have this chip in them it's
20 or 30 or 40 dollars to purchase
a high end development board is about
80 to 85 dollars that with a little
more memory and a little more flash
we also do support one of the IDT network processors
as well as the
Broadcom
5000 6000 cores the Broadcom 4000
cores has a
number of bugs in its
pipelining so it requires
changes to
GCC and Binutils to schedule
instructions correctly and appropriately
unfortunately these compilers changes whenever
donated back to the SFS or the FSF for inclusion
in these projects
in a timely fashion so they are not in
the base and the patches don't exist for the
versions of the compilers that are in FreeBSD
so if we are to support this kernel
we would need some kind of
out of tree tools
and general the project tries not
to do that although as we move in
to the embedded environment we may be
forced to do that more and more
so here is a rundown of the different
pieces of the ADM5120 that supports the basics
the only thing that these boards have is
that is significant that
isn't supported right now is USB
nobody who has done
development has had a board
with USB on it so we don't support USB
on the IDT the NIC
and the serial console are working there's
support for adding devices
on the PCI bus
the router board
the RB532
is one of the commercially available boards that has
this chip on it
it's not a particularly common chip
but Wojciech Koszek
had one of these laying around
and decided hey
I'll get FreeBSD working on that it's
well documented and he was able to do this
again some more details on the Broadcom platform
interesting things to note here is that
Broadcom MIPS have a relatively unique
they have a way you could actually
enumerate all the devices that are
into the system object
and most of the other systems that are available
you'll have
to know oh I'm on MPC8548
our PC I have this device at this address
this device at this address and whatever
you have to compile in tables
but Broadcom products
you can go and ask
what devices are out there?
and enumerate through them
and we support doing that
in a lot of ways it's like PCI
where you can ask each individual device
what's your ID and it comes back with an ID
you can use that to select the proper driver
for each of the devices
so work is currently underway
and this is in various degrees of completion
there's some work being done to get the Broadcom
6000 series working well
Cavium networks
has a full
Octeon port that supports
all the
members of the Octeon family
supports all the auxiliary
hardware that is on that
all the network packet
engine technology all the crypto technology
that the MIPS
multi-core MIPS products have
one problem though is
that it was taken with the old MIPS 2 snapshot
and it is against FreeBSD that's about
22 months old at this point
so even though the port itself is fairly good
but it's a fairly old version of
FreeBSD so
it's a lot of work to bring it forward
I'm working on the Audigy
Au 1xxx port
which is languishing for a lack lo time
Oleksandr Tymoshenko has gone to work with
a couple of other people
whose name are escaping me Dan White
um-hum
yeah just look Dan on the new Atheros
AR7000 and
AR9000 parts
so this is just a
wondering list of what I'm working on
you can read it or I can read it
so I'll just go to the next slide
we have a pseudo console working
we have the NIC working
there's some stability issues
that Oleksandr is
looking into he's trying to figure out
what's causing the underling
stability issues
this work is being done in the
FreeBSD SVN repository
although not in the naming tree
one of the things that
the project has done is it's transition of most
of the use of Perforce into subversion
so there's a project MIPS tree that this work
is being done in if you want to
check it out and look at it for yourself
the Cavium port I talked about a little bit
it supports all 3 ABIs
but its either or it doesn't support
all 3 at the same time
you can either have an o32 system
or a n32 system or a n64 system
so that portion of the
port needs some additional work
before we can roll it into the system
one of the other interesting things is
that this port you can build entirely on a Linux system
you don't need a FreeBSD system to host it
normally with FreeBSD
you have to build FreeBSD on FreeBSD
people have either
FreeBSD boxes or virtual machines
around to build it
and ported in network tools
like NetBSD has done
so that you can build an environment that's
more foreign than just FreeBSD
and the last item
Cavium has Cavium MIPS isn't like other MIPS
in some ways there are a number of extensions to the MIPS
ISAs that Cavium has done to improve performance
to get better
validation semantics than you can have from
normal MIPS instructions so
this port also makes use of those
so that needs the special tools from Cavium
fortunately Cavium is giving
their technology pushed back into
the FSF releases
unfortunately it's being
pushed back to GPLP 3 versions
so
I'm not sure exactly how the project
would deal with that the patches they have
will use GPLP 2 code, so those can potentially
can come into the project
RMI has a
FreeBSD 6.1 port they are trying to
work with the project to get into the tree
to put hardware into the project cluster so that they
can be well supported by the project that code is not
yet available even to the internal developers
who are still talking and trying to make it all happen
I talked about that
there's a number of items that needs to be done for
the next port as it exists in Perforce sorry
as it exists in the
FreeBSD subversion tree
the first one is that we need to
get a n32 and n64 support working
along with Multilib support in the tool chain so that
we can have the different ABIs coexist on the platform
we have a
emulation working configuration with FreeBSD MIPS
you can run FreeBSD MIPS emulation if you want to try it out or
your developing the code QEMU
is a little bit more widely deployed
and we'll like to have a configuration that works with that
right now there's a number of
problems relating to interrupts that need to be solved
and looked at
we also need to have 64-bit PMAP support with some
rudiments of that in code right now but it's not enough
to bring up
64-bit kernel 64-bit user space
and
we need to take
the SMP code either from the Cavium port
and make it work so that we can take
advantage of the multicore processors
one of the nice things about the FreeBSD project
is that we've got
good scalability on Intel
and we would presume that scalability would translate to
multicore systems in the embedded world and we would like to
take advantage of all the work that's being done
on Intel servers or the embedded space try to capture
some of the
embedded market, finally
we need more
we need more support from system on chips
that's going to be a
a continuing battle
new parts are released all the time
FreeBSD needs to be ported to those
and in the embedded world it's a bit different than on Intel
where everything has a standard address you have
standard devices
in the embedded world is not very
convenient to the embedded designer
if they can save a little bit of money by putting something
in a different location they will so each new
processors each new chip comes out we need to take the time
to sit down and get
FreeBSD working on that so that wraps up some of the general
MIPS history and that kind of occurred status support
we are going to talk a little bit about some
of the items that are relatively new to
FreeBSD that would make it attractive for embedding
or running in an embedded environment
the PowerPC and ARM architecture have a number
of things that have been added lately
Rahul was talking about some of the prescale
improvements for multicore
high-end powerful chips and
in an earlier talk
there's some other things I'll talk about here in a second
one of the things that I just
committed to the tree is the ability to build
the system compilers
for other architectures so you can use them as a
cross compiler
natively rather than carry inside
the FreeBSD
build system again this is similar to
a lot of the build technology that
NetBSD has done for sometime
and that is the first step towards making
ports cross buildable
right now there are
three basic classes of ports
there are the ports that have, are really stupid
that just compiled a lot of .C programs
those are very easy to point
and let the cross compiler
those just work
there's a class of ports that have been written
specifically
to understand
the new naming conventions
and you tell it
I want to compile
for an ARM
FreeBSD and it knows how to find
that compiler and build for it
some of those ports work if you pass
the right configure arguments on the command-line
and then there's a class of ports in the middle that
they build tools to build the rest of the port
and these tools need to run natively
but they don't have any support for cross building so
it uses the target compiler
the try to build the .h files
or
whatever for the program to build
the .h files or whatever they are using but when
that program goes to run you get an error
because you can't run
it on binary on an x86 machine also in the
third class of ports are
there's a number of ports that try to do
cross-compilation
and got it wrong
so that it just don't work
so some of the other things in FreeBSD that
are interesting to the embedded world are
we're starting to get a number of support for
a number of different devices and technologies
I went into some of these in my paper
I'll highlight a few of them here one of the
most important is the NOR flash support in
a lot of the low end routers switches that are
wireless access points that are available
they load off of NOR flash so having new drivers
for that allows us
to get into that market and we can boot off of them
we can manipulate the underlying flash
we do not yet have a flash file system,
we really need one talk
about that a little bit more
in the embedded world pin count really really matters so
a lot of the devices are serial devices
and FreeBSD has got better
support for different serial protocols
that has recently had a new
USB stack integrated into the tree
we've had improvements to the I2C
support we've got rudiment we've got new support
for I2S for the sound devices on both embedded systems
and coincidentally on old
Macintosh laptops
we've got support for
the SPI bus which is a synchronous bus we've permanently
flashed a couple of other specialized devices
for years FreeBSD has also booted well
with a Compact Flash on a x86 machine
while in the embedded space
Compact Flash isn't very well favored
because it's a 50 pin interface
but the SD cards that you find in your cameras are
very well favored because it's a
very small footprint and also it has 9 pins
you can implement it in I think 4 or 5 pins
which makes it fairly attractive and low cost high
storage medium and FreeBSD
has a good SD stack
we recently added support
for the high-capacity
SD cards and for MMC cards
finally a lot of the
embedded systems
are wireless
have some kind of wireless technology
and FreeBSD has a fairly good
wireless access stack
access point stack written by Sam Leffler
so I'm mentioning it here as well
there's a number of features that
are private or in another stacks
on PowerPC there's a number of additional cores
that are supported
in addition to the free scale parts which are
the top portion the E500 is a it's called a
core
presented this in a lot of detail so I'll just skim
over it these are all the ones that are listed
also been instrumental in driving
some of the other
PowerPC chip-sets
the AMCC 440
support he's been working on has
it booting single user or multiuser?
has it booting multiuser off of a USB
flash, last summer he sponsored a student
on the E300 yeah it's the E300 and the MPC5200
that is
to bring up the FreeBSD on
the MPC5200 which is an E300 core it has an
number of differences between the 500 core
like
explained there's a
number of things that are optional or different in the
specification you need to code for
there's been some additional floating point support
that's gone in and there's some work underway for
the G5 Mac not embedded power platform
but some additional PowerPC
infrastructure that's going well
FreeBSD ARM
has recently gotten Marvel support for the
different members of the Orion family
there's three families of processors Orion,
Kirkwood, and Discovery
that are supported
managed to get into the tree
so
this company does really good work
there's also support for Samsung devices that are in the
Openmoko
and a couple of other boards
Sam Leffler recently added support
to the IXP 435 on Xscale boards chips
and there's some more
underway to get the Cirrus Logic family of ARM
9 parts to get into the tree
although that work is stalled the
team working on it ran out of time
got interested in other things
so there's a number of things
that the embedded world will be
very happy if FreeBSD did and
the biggest one is probably the
flash file system support
FreeBSD needs to have a flash
file system
with the number of
people talking about porting one from Linux or
using the same understructure as
one of the Linux file systems
no need to completely reinvent the wheel here
in addition to some of the technical
challenges that we have we need
greater marketing and out reach and documentation
to show people that this is possible
and a reasonable thing to do
so that's the end of my talk
I guess it's now the time for
questions
and here are the links again
to the paper and the slides
because that was what I put on the slides
will also work equally well
there's no slide intended
there was talk for a while of using DesktopBSD
to do the packeting for the embedded
to add some nice attributes
so any
of those technologies that would enable that
anything that works will be a reasonable thing
are there any difficulties in common with
bringing up an embedded system
from one SSC to another to a third or is every
effort
completely different from
in terms of implementation and the problems you run into
I can answer that question yes
there are a number of things unique to each
individual
SSC there are
quarks in the silica there are quarks in the
cores implementation of the architecture you're trying
to do
those are almost never uncommon
writing crazy things
one of the problems that we have with FreeBSD
is adding additional
buses is a big
copy and paste operation now
takes about 200 lines to implement a new bus
which should take about 10
so that's one thing that's in common with those
between bringing up different processes
also you tend to use the same kind of tools
the Jtag Reader
the Jtag Debugger typically
on a well resourced operation
to bring up the different processes
the different cores when you are doing the initial core
the answer varies and people have written
entire books on how to do that
some in common some very unique
and will like to make the things
that are incommon and hard easier
to the extent that we can
one of the things is that it takes a lot
of work to bring them up
are there other questions
how about the
multicore scalability
of FreeBSD
right now we don't know
how well FreeBSD MIPS will scale
we don't know whether
there are bottle necks in
the PMAP for example we think it would be
fairly well once we've carried on and get to the start
that isn't working now debugged
It'll be comparable to x86 there
may need to be a period of tuning
because the minute we implement one of the atomic
primitives effecting performance of the other
potential problem is cache coherency some
MIPS processors have really good
cache coherency for
multi-processing others push
a lot of the burden of that on to the implement
Cavium will probably scale really
well because it is fairly coherent
the MIPS with a fairly coherent cache policy
and architecture
it's really the only MIPS one multi-core MIPS that I'm
really familiar with I don't know how the others will work
any other questions ?
OK thank you very much